Hello, I am Kovid Goyal, the creator of Kitty. In this video, I will give you a brief tour
of Kitty's productivity enhancing features. Kitty started as a personal project to enhance
my own terminal experience, but has since grown into something used by thousands of people
the world over. Kitty is designed for terminal power users, people who, like me, prefer to
spend the entire day in the terminal and use the terminal for every task imaginable. Kitty has
many features and niceties that make this kind of workflow both more productive and more fun.
Let's start with something simple. Often, when running commands in the terminal, it so happens
that a command produces lots of output and takes a long time to run. You might find yourself
wanting to examine that output in more detail. You can, of course, scroll up and just look at the
output, but sometimes it's useful to open it in an editor or a pager and say search through it
or filter it. Kitty has a built-in feature wherein if you press the Control Shift and G key,
the output from the last command opens in the pager. As you can see here, the output from the
ls command is opened in a pager: less, in my case. This is not limited to just the last command. You
can actually scroll up and here you can see a compile output from building Kitty to examine the
output of any previous command. You hold the Control Shift key and right click on the output
and there you go. It opens in the pager as before. I can now search through it or refer to it
to my heart's content. You can even use Kitty's multiple windows feature to have the pager window
pop up as a separate window. You can see here there are now two windows. One has the original shell
and one has the output from the clicked command open in a pager. I can scroll through this
output and refer to it while typing future commands. I find this facility extremely handy and
use it several times every day. Note that this feature is implemented in Kitty by means of
shell integration. Shell integration means that Kitty works with common shells such as bash,
Z shell, fish etc. to enable this and other niceties. For example, you will notice that the current
working directory is shown in the window title bar. If I change to some other directory,
the window title bar changes. Similarly, if I run a command, say for example, sleep,
the name of the command shows up in the window title bar while it's running. Once the sleep is over,
the title bar goes back to the working directory. This is a small example of some of Kitty's
productivity features that make working the terminal all day much more fun and productive.
Now, let's try something a little more fancy. Consider that most quotidian of terminal
experiences listing files. So here we go. Let's list some files.
Looks pretty standard so far. A rather colorful list of files and a couple of directories.
The fun starts when you click on one of these files. So for example, let's see how Kitty is
launched. Holding down the control shift keys, I click on it. And as you can see,
the launcher.c file has opened up in my editor of choice, which is vim. And I can edit it to do
whatever. Simply by clicking on the file. And that's not all. You can even click on an image.
For example, let's click on the Kitty logo. And there we go. It opens in the terminal. You can view
the image. So as you can see, simply clicking on files on the listing, you can open them.
And of course, Kitty is meant for power users, which means that you don't have to use the mouse.
You can instead press control shift P and Y. And it lists all the files with a number
next to their names. So for example, if I press six, once again, the Kitty logo opens up.
These features are powered by two things. The first is the ls command has a
facility to output hyperlinks. So let's see
here the ls command on my computer. As you can see here, as the hyperlink auto flag
added to it, this means that every file that ls lists is actually a hyperlink. You can see
that it gets underlined when you move the mouse over it. The second thing that makes this possible
is a piece of configuration in Kitty called open-actions.conf. In this file, you can tell Kitty
what to do when you open a file, for example, by clicking on it. So here, you can see that this
entry on this line tells Kitty that for files of my type text, open it in the editor in an overlay
window, which means a window overlayed on the current window. Similarly, image files are opened
in Kitty itself using the icat kitten and so on. This entry here is of particular interest. It uses
another kitten, which is a small program that's part of Kitty, to allow you to directly click on
search results from a grep tool and open them in an editor. So let's see that in action.
Here we go. Let me run my grep tool, which, and search for say, hyperlink.
Here you can see a bunch of results. So moving the mouse over these results, they get underlined,
indicating they're clickable. So let's open this one and there you see it has opened in the editor
right on the click line. This is extremely convenient to inserting through files in the terminal.
This in turn is powered by, let's see here what we have and the kitten. Now kittens are small
kitty programs that enhance its functionality. So here the kitten is the hyperlinked grep kitten.
So what that does is it takes the output from a grep program and adds hyperlinks to it so that
they become clickable when displayed in Kitty. So as you can see here, these simple features that
are designed in a composable and modular way allow you to greatly enhance the experience of
using a terminal. Since we have been talking of hyperlinks, let's note that the usefulness
is not limited only to the local machine. You can even use them over SSH connections to remote
servers. So for example, let me SSH into one of my servers and do an ls hyperlink auto.
You can see some files have been listed. One of them is an image. Let's click on this image and
see what happens. As you can see it opens up in a kitty kitten. This is the remote file kitten
and it gives you some options for what you want to do with the image. You can edit it. You can
open it. You can save it to your local computer. So let's choose to open it to view the file locally.
There we go. The remote file kitten seamlessly downloads the image in the background and opens it
locally on the local computer. This is useful if particularly for viewing a complicated file such as
images, videos, etc. that the remote server may not be able to handle. But the remote file kitten
is not limited simply to opening. You can also edit files. So for example, here we have a simple
text file. Let's click on it and once again the remote file kitten opens.
It gives you the option to edit the file. So let's choose that option by pressing the E key.
You can see that the kitten downloads the file and let's make some changes to it.
Notice that this is running in vim on my local machine with all the customization and
facilities available. Let me save and quit vim. The remote file kitten automatically
updates the file on the server. Let's cat it again. And you see that the file has been edited
as expected. This is really useful if you tend to spend a lot of time SSH
into servers and you need to edit, make a one off edit using a fancy editor or similar.
I should note that as far as it comes to images, you can actually view images directly over
SSH connections thanks to yet another kitten, the icat image viewing kitten in kitty. We'll discuss
that and some more fancy kittens in the following segment.
Now it's time to have some fun with images. I know terminals are text devices but sometimes
it's cool to be able to display images and even useful if you're SSH into a remote computer.
I need to quickly look at a graph or a report that's available as an image.
So without further ado, let's see how we do that. We use the icat kitten which is a
small program written that's distributed as part of kitty that can display images within kitty.
Here I'll display the kitty logo as you can see shows up as an image in the right there in the
terminal itself. The icat kitten can also download images from the internet and display them.
Here we'll see it doing that with an animated gif of a Rubik's cube. I have icat
aliased as just the icat command on my computer.
So here you see it downloaded the Rubik's cube and it's displaying the animation. The animation
will continue playing even while you type other commands. The kitty graphics protocol that powers
the icat kitten is integrated with many other programs. For example, the Ranger file manager.
Here you see we've opened a folder full of images. And as you scroll through the files,
Ranger displays thumbnails of the images using the kitty graphics protocol right there in the
terminal. Another cool feature of the kitty graphics protocol is that it works over SSH. So if I
SSH into one of my servers and run icat Athenaum.jpg, you see that the image is displayed directly
in the terminal even though it's on a remote server. The image data is sent over the TTY pipe
over SSH. When running locally, the graphics protocol is smart enough to avoid the overhead of
doing this and to use the local file system to display images. Another cool kitten that kitty has
is the unicode input kitten, which you can use to input arbitrary unicode symbols, emoji, etc.
into your terminal. Just press control shift U and then type the name of the symbol you want. So
for example, here we have a cat. We can insert a cat face with tears of joy into our terminal
and there you have it right there at the prompt. You can search for all sorts of symbols. Here we have
some beer. Let's celebrate this great kitten right here. So this is useful. If you find yourself
doing a lot of chatting using terminal chat programs such as WeChat and you want to send your
buddies emoji or other other symbols. We have talked a fair bit about kittens and how they can
be used to enhance the terminal experience. Now let's discuss something more basic window management.
Kitty has the ability to tile multiple windows next to each other and manage them using flexible
layouts. You can also create multiple tabs. So let's create some windows by pressing control shift
enter. You see we have three windows tiles next to each other. We can create some new tabs as well.
The tabs are displayed at the bottom. The tab titles show the current working directory
or actually whatever title the program running in the shell sets. So let's close these tabs.
Get back to the windows. As you can see these windows are tiled next to each other. You can press
control shift and the window number to switch to a window. So one for the first two for the second
three for the third and so on. You can even visually shift by pressing control shift F7 and simply
typing the number of the window you want to shift to. Now while we are discussing multiple windows
let's look at a cool feature whereby we can type in one window and have the text appear in all
the windows simultaneously. This is useful if you want to do a poor man's automation of multiple
servers for example. To do this let's open the kitty shell which we can do by pressing control shift
escape. The kitty shell is a shell where you can issue commands to kitty itself to make it do things.
So here let's first change the layout to grid which works better with four windows
and now to actually broadcast the text we need to launch the broadcast kitten which we can do
like this. And we see that we have a broadcast window available at which we can type. Let me type
the command ls. You see that ls has been typed in every single window. You can backspace and it works
as expected. Let's execute the ls command and we see that the ls has been executed in every window
showing different outputs. Let's clear out these outputs and end the broadcast session.
So as you can see here the kitty shell is quite a powerful tool.
A note that the shell is powered by something called the kitty remote control protocol.
This allows you to control kitty from other shells, other terminals, programs running on your
computer etc. And this is very powerful. Anything you can do in the shell you can also do
via the remote control facility. Let's have a quick look at it. Change the layout to stack so we
focused on the shell window. Let's see some commands. So here you can see a list of commands
available in the shell. You can do things like create new windows, set window titles, set window
logos, send text to windows, set change the opacity, select windows, all sorts of things resize them,
send signals to children running in windows etc. You can change the colors, you can run kittens,
and on and on and on. So this forms a general scripting ability for kitty and allows you to
control kitty and automate various tasks in it. Your imagination is the limit when it comes to
use cases. Since this is supposed to be a brief tour I think I'll end here but before I go
let's see how to bling-up the kitty terminal a bit by changing its colors. Kitty actually has
a themes kitten that has a large collection of themes downloaded from a central repository.
Let's run it and see what happens. So here you can see there are literally hundreds of themes
organized by dark and light colors. You can choose a theme you want. So for example I like
Belafonte. So let's change to that by pressing the Enter key and then the M key to tell the kitten
to modify kitty.com to make the change permanent and you see that kitty now uses the Belafonte theme.
Note that the kitten can actually be run non interactively as well. So for example if you specify
the theme name on the command line it will change the theme directly without running interactively.
You can actually choose where all to change the colors either in the current terminal or
all running terminals on your system. So as you can see the themes kitten is a nice way to
make your terminal experience a little more colorful. I personally use it to adjust the colors
to the time of day so that the screen ambient brightness is the best match for my eyes.
And I think with that I'll say goodbye and thank you and hope you enjoy using kitty.